Guide to the the Department Store and Office Workers' Organizing Collection TAM.002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Department Store and Office Workers' Organizing Collection
1916-1947
1930-1941
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Department Store Employees Union and Office Workers' Union
Rand School of Social Science
TAM.002
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Efforts to unionize New York City department store employees in the 1930s took place under the auspices of the Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250 (at first affiliated with the American Federation of Labor, and subsequently with the Congress of Industrial Organizations) and the Office Workers' Union, an affiliate of the Trade Union Unity League, a Communist Party labor initiative. The collection contains pamphlets, leaflets, newsletters and clippings relating to sit-down strikes, department store and office workers strikes and organizing in the 1930s, printed material from the Office Workers' Union, and of the Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250.
Custodial History
The Department Store and Office Workers' Organizing Collection was transferred from the Rand School Archives in 1963. The original donor to the Rand School is unknown.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Efforts to unionize New York City department store employees in the 1930s took place under the auspices of the Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250, at first affiliated with the American Federation of Labor. The local became a CIO affiliate in 1937 and later expanded into Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union. The Office Workers' Union, a Communist Party labor initiative and an affiliate of the Trade Union Unity League, also organized workers in department stores, as well as clerical staff in a variety of businesses including newspapers, insurance and mail order companies.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains pamphlets, leaflets, newsletters and clippings relating to sit-down strikes, department store and office workers strikes and organizing in the 1930s. Also included is printed material from the Office Workers' Union and the Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250 including some agreements. General information on AFL and CIO unions, TUUL strikes, sit-down strikes, coal strikes, and longshoremen's strikes in California and Hawaii is also included.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, General Files
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transfer from the Rand School Archives, 1963. The accession number associated with this collection is 1963.002
Pamphlets.; Collective labor agreements.; Newsletters.; Clippings (information artifacts); Strikes and lockouts |x Retail trade |z New York (State) |z New York.; Labor unions and communism -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Sit-down strikes |z New York (State) |z New York.; Department stores |x Employees |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Rand School of Social Science; Trade Union Unity League (U.S.); Office Workers' Union; Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union
- Series I: General Files.
  - American Federation of Labor: Statistics, Programs, Bibliography, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Communist Party: Ohracle (Ohrbach's employees newsletter), May 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations and Independent Unions: Affiliation Listings, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250: 1250 Organizer (newsletter), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250: A & S Chapter - A & S Beacon (newsletter), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250: Bulletin (newsletter), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250: General Correspondence and Contracts, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250: Hearn's Department Stores Contracts, 1935, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250: Leaflets, undated, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250: Macy's Chapter - R.H. Macy Unionizer (newsletter), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250: Newspaper Clippings, 1934-1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250: Ohrbach's - Ben Goodman Case, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250: Pitkin Avenue Woolworth, 5310 Chapter - 1250 Chain (newsletter), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Department Store Employees Union, Local 1250: Stern Chapter - Stern News (newsletter), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Department Stores: Organizing Information, undated, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Labor Research Association: "Labor Developments in 1940" (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - National Industrial Conference Board and National Negro Congress, 1938, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - National Recovery Administration: Code of Fair Competition for the Retail Trade, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - New Era Retail Clerks Union of America: Meeting Notice, May 1937 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Office Workers' Union: Clippings, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Office Workers' Union: Leaflets, undated, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Office Workers' Union: Office Worker (newsletter), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Office Workers' Union, Accountants Section: Leaflets, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: A & S Local - We Declare (newsletter), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Bloomingdale's Local - Bloomingdale's Own Brand (newsletter), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Gimbel Local (Leaflets), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Hearn Local (Leaflets), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Klein Local (Leaflets), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Leaflets, undated, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Lerner Group (Leaflets), undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Lerner Group - Lerner Worker (newsletter), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Macy Group (Leaflets & Newspaper Clippings), undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Macy Group - The Macy Worker (newsletter), 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Martin's Local - Martin's Events (newsletter), undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Namm Local (Leaflets), undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Ohrbach Local (Leaflets), undated, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Ohrbach Local - The Green Box Moves On (newsletter), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Office Workers' Union, Department Store Section: Petrie-Red Robin Local (Leaflets), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Office Workers' Union, Dry Goods Section: Leaflets, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Office Workers' Union, Industrial Agents Chapter: Leaflets, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Office Workers' Union, Insurance Chapter: Leaflets, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Office Workers' Union: Jewish Morning Journal Strike (Leaflets), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Office Workers' Union, Literary Trades Section: American Mercury Strike (Leaflets), undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Office Workers' Union, National Bellas Hess Section: Leaflet, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Office Workers' Union, Newspaper Section: Leaflets, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Office Workers' Union, Receiving Department Workers Section: Receiving News (newsletter), undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Office Workers' Union, Wall Street Section: Leaflets, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Retail Clerks International Protective Association (AFL), 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - San Francisco Department Store Strike: Statistics and History, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Sit-Down Strikes: Bibliographies and Outline for Study, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Sit-Down Strikes: House of Representatives, Resolutions and Remarks, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Sit-Down Strikes: Legal Opinions, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Sit-Down Strikes: Papers, 1937, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Strikes, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Strikes, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Strikes, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Strikes, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Strikes, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Strikes, Jan 1941-May 1941 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Strikes: Coal Workers, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Strikes: Dock Workers of California and Hawaii, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Strikes: Red International of Labor Unions, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Strikes: Newspaper Clippings (Ohrbach's and Klein's), 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Strikes: Trade Union Unity League, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Strikes: White Collar and Professional Workers, 1934-Mar 1936 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - United Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Employees Union: Publications, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Works Progress Administration: Union Protests against Curtailment Program, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 67)